<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[These ben the ordynau[n]ces, that the emperour hath caused to be red and declared in his presence, to thestates of his countrees of those partyes at theyr assemblynge to his magestye the .vii. day of Octobre, the yere of our Lorde .M.V.C.xxxi. ... ]</title>
            <author>Holy Roman Empire. Emperor (1519-1556 : Charles V)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1532</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18447.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117941</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853150</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 61:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[These ben the ordynau[n]ces, that the emperour hath caused to be red and declared in his presence, to thestates of his countrees of those partyes at theyr assemblynge to his magestye the .vii. day of Octobre, the yere of our Lorde .M.V.C.xxxi. ... ]</title>
                  <author>Holy Roman Empire. Emperor (1519-1556 : Charles V)</author>
                  <author>Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor, 1500-1558.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xliiii leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Imprynted by me Robert wyer, dwellynge at the sygne of saynt Ioh[a]n Eua[n]gelyst, i[n] saynt Martyns parysshe in the bysshop of Norwytche rentes besyde charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1532?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and adress from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 5015.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 5016 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect as filmed: title page lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Reformation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe ben the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, that the Emperour hath cauſed to be red and delared in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſince / to the ſtates of his countr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes at theyr aſſemblynge to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtye the .vii. day of Octobre / the yere of our Lorde. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.v.C.vvvi. The whiche haue be publyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed through all the ſayd countrees the .xv. day of Nouembre folowynge / aſwell to the auoydynge of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>herayn ſecte / and other reproued ſectes / as for the pourueyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the dyſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of his Coyne &amp; ordres to be ſette in the ſayde Countrees.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regali.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:3"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Harles by the dyuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne clemency Emperour of the Romaynes euer Auguſt kynge of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many / of Caſtyl / of Le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / of garnado / of Ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gon / of Nauarre / of Naples / of Cecylle of Maillorke / of Sardayn / of Yles of Yndes / and mayn lande of the Occyan ſee / Archeduke of Auſtryche / Duke of Burgoyn / of Latheryc / of Brabant / of Lembourg / of Luxembourg. &amp;c. ¶ Erle of Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dres / of Artoys / of Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>goyn palentyn / of Henau / of Hollande o / zelande / of Ferrette / of Hagnenault / of Namur. &amp;c. ¶ Prynce of zwaue / Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kys of the holy Empyre / lorde of Fryſe / of Salyns / of Malynes / of the Cyties / and townes of Vtryght / &amp; doneryſſell. And domynatour in Aſye / &amp; in Affry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke</signed>
               <salute>to all that theſe preſentes ſhall ſe / gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>For to vnderſtande and eſchewe redreſſe the Errours and abuſyons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge our holy fayth lykely for to come in our countrees in theſe partyes. To the
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:18518:3"/>
abuſyons beynge in our ſayd countrees vpon the feate of coynes of moneys / v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the dyuerſytees of cuſtomes that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben vſed. Of the abuſyon of Notary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es and ſcrybes. Of ingratynge aſwell of vytaylles as of other marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. Of bankerotes. Of vacabondes. Of drynkynges / &amp; dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſes. Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayaunce of horſes out of our ſayd coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees. To the dyſordre of araye agaynſt blaſphemers &amp; opprobryers of our lorde god / of the vyrgyn mary / and of ſayntꝭ w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great irreuerence to our mother holy Churche / and of her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementꝭ in great dyſeſtymacyon of our ordynauncꝭ and to the great hynderaunces or interre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes of our ſubgectes. The whiche for to ordre / and to adreſſe a good true / and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le amyte &amp; intellygence in our ſayd coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees amonge &amp; bytwene our ſubgectes / we haue cauſed to propoſe to the eſtates of our ſayd countrees / and gyuen theym by wrytynge at theyr laſte aſſemble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs certayne poyntes and artycles / and vpon the ſame to haue theyr aduyſe
<pb facs="tcp:18518:4"/>
the whiche they haue ſatyſfyed. Lettyng you to wyt that this aforeſayd conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (ſeynge the ſayd aduyſe of the premyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes in our pryue counceyll typely tryed / We contynuynge in our pourpoſe for the honoure &amp; reuerence of god our creatoure and to the exaſtacion of his fayth / to the expulſyng and extynctyon of the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rayn ſectes and other abuſed ſectꝭ to the welth and profyte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men welth / to the ſupporte and eaſe of our ſubgectes from all wronges and oppreſſyons / to theyr ſurete and reſt / and for remedye to the ſayd abuſyons aboueſayd / by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe of the knyghtꝭ of our ordre / &amp; of many other good &amp; notable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones of our ſayd countrees / the whiche we haue for the ſame aſſembled and conuocate: And with great &amp; rype delyberacion haue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned and ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe actes folowynge. </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:18518:4"/>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Charles. &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Yrſte as touchynge the Lutherayn ſect &amp; other reproued ſectꝭ / that our ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces conteyned i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our laſt lettres of pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carde gyuen the .xiiii. daye of Octobre / the yere of our Lorde .M.v.L.xxix. vpon the abuſyng of our holy catholyke fayth / and auoydyng the peruers ſect of Martyn Luther and other reproued auctoures by our mother holy Churche / than and ſythen publyſſhed in theſe ſayd countrees and ſeygnouryes. And by vs reuewed in fourme and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner / as in our preſence we haue this ſayd day cauſed to be red to the Eſtates of our ſayde countrees here aſſembled with vs to be obſerued / kepte / and maynteyned accordynge to theyr fourme and tenoure and that the penalyties therin declared &amp; put to the offender to be really and rygo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rouſly executed without remyſſyon / dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſymulacyon or delay. And to the ende that none ſhall pretende ygnouraunce / 
<pb facs="tcp:18518:5"/>
we haue wylled and ordeyned our ſayd ordynaunces to be publyſſhed thorowe all our ſayd countrees and lordſhyppes (in theſe coſtes) within all places where as Proclamacions ben wont to be done the .xv. daye of the nexte moneth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uembre. And fro that tyme euery .vi. mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth tyll by vs be otherwyſe ordeyned.</p>
               <p>¶And as touchynge the act of Coynes and money / we do ordeyne that the ordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce vpon the ſame reuewed in four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and maner as we haue cauſed to be red to the ſayd eſtates confermally at the laſte ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the .x. day of Decembre the yere .xv.C.xxvi. rypely delyberate by thaduyſe of all the eſtates of our ſayd countrees / of dyuerſe other perſones ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge knowlege in feates of Coynes &amp; moneyes / of the generalles or mayſters of the ſayde Coynes / of the knyghtes of our ordre / and of the chyef of our preuye counceyll / and of reaſourers / to be in al poyntes and artycles obſerued and kept And for bycauſe that no ꝑſone ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tende
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:18518:5"/>
ygnoraunce: we wyll that it be pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyſſhed in al places / as is aforeſayd. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>¶ And for remedy to be had in abuſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s procedynge of the dyuerſyte of the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of our ſayd countrees / &amp; to the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyences that by theym dayly enſue in ſo moche as oftentymes dyuerſe pure cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtomes contrarye in one countree be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyned and veryfyed by dyuerſe practy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyens. And by the ſayd meanes many of oure ſubgectes do leſe theyr ryght to the great dyſprofyte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men welthe.</p>
               <p>The defaute wherof is that the ſayd cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes be not approued and remaynyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge in wrytynge. We haue therfore ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the cuſtomes of all our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees in theſe coſtes within .vi. monethes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuynge ſhallbe put in wrytynge by the offycers and men of lawe in all the tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of oure ſayd countrees great &amp; ſmall And eche of the ſame for the ſayde tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / theyr ſheryffes or bayllyes / and all other offycers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr townes where they haue admynyſtracyon and rule reſpecty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely
<pb facs="tcp:18518:6"/>
to put the ſayd cuſtomes in wrytyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge accorded in euery quarter: and to bryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge them to our preſence: and in our abſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to our right dere and beloued ſyſter the quene Regent for vs to cauſe them to be vyſyted and dewely examyned. And vpon the ſame to take aduyſe of our pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyncyall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyllers / and other as nede ſhall be / &amp; with good &amp; rype delyberacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of counceyll to conferme and ordeyne vpon the ſayd cuſtomes obſeruacyon of the ſame accordynge to equyte and reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And for the moſt profyte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte of our ſubgectes in that behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of notaryes and ſcryueners.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd to pouruey agaynſte the faultes and wronges done in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees by Notaryes or commyn wryters: ſome of them by ſympleneſſe and ygnoraunce / and other by delyberate dede to the great hynderau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and loſſe of our ſubgectes / and of the
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:18518:6"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welthe. We haue therfore enacted that from henſforth none ſhall be admyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in to that towme / but well lerned men and of good fame / and ſuche as by examynacyon of the cheyfe men of our prouyncyall counſeyl &amp; Iuges of euery countree ſhall be founde experte / able / &amp; ſuffycye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / and approued / and that it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere by acte of the ſayde counſeyll and prouyncyall Iuges. And the ſayde acte by the ſayde notaryes (or they may excer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyſe the ſayde towne) ſhal be bounde to leue in the courte rolles of the ſayd coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeyll and to paye for euery acte onely .x. grotes of flaundres / and vpon payne arbytrary that none of both partyes pay or take more then the ſayde .x. grotes for an acte. And we forbyd all other not ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amyned and admytted as is aforeſayd to the rowme or offyce of notary or wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter vpon payne aforeſayd and to be dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amyted for euer to excercyſe that offyce nor other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of Marchaundyſes engrated.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:7"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the domages procedynge &amp; that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopole or engratyng whiche dyuerſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntꝭ and other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfycers of our countrees in theſe coſtes / vſe dayly as well feates of vytaylles as other wares &amp; marchaundyſes in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe maners. And to pouruey agaynſt the vnlefull bargaynes that many do / for theyr ſynguler profyte / to the great hynderaunce of good and faythfull mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes our ſubgectes and other conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte in our countrees here aboute &amp; of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welthe. We of our ſentence &amp; abſolute power hath enacted for euer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no College of marchauntes of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes nor ſtraungers of any felawſhyp / theyr brokers / legers / helpers / nor lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe artificers nor other of what ſoeuer vacacyon faculte he be of / medle to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſtatute / ordynaunce or couencyon ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge engratyng or monopole to make bargaynes contractes or pactyons vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:18518:7"/>
/ To haue ſecrete knowleges / as byenge all one ſorte of ware or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyſe / and kepe it vnder them. And by that meanes to put &amp; kepe other that haue nede therof in neceſſyte / &amp; conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne them to bye the ſayd wares at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyfe &amp; vnreſonable pryce / at the plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of the ſayd regratours / and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende and forbyd theym and all other to make and practyke all other lyke damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable and peruycyous pactyons / contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes and abuſyons to the domage of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welth / vpon payne of banyſſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and confyſcacyon of goodes / coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees and places / or confyſcacyon of pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / and other arbytraryly accordynge to theffect of the myſdede. And we forbyd all iuges / offycers / and to all our lyege men and lawyers / and all other of our ſayde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees: and to all them hauynge or pretendyng auctoryte to ordayne / ena<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cte / conferme / or make any ſuche puycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and vnreſonable ſtatutꝭ concernyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſuche monopole. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyng them expreſſely that yf any ſuch ſtatutes com
<pb facs="tcp:18518:8"/>
afore them to be broken and abolyſſhed And of our parte we haue declared and do declare them none &amp; of no valoure.</p>
               <p>And as moche as nede is we haue reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and fordone them by theſe preſentes In gyuynge charge to all our pouruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and eche of them in his behalfe that where as our offycers or other be necly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to do and fulfyll this our wyl that in this caſe they procede agaynſt them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be neclygent or delayers in doynge that / that they ought to do without dyſſymu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacyon as they fynde them: this to be don at all tymes / and agaynſt them that do conſtytute or conferme any peruycyons ordynaunce or ſtatute aforeſayd / or that directly or indirectly do agaynſt this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent ordynaunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of derth of vytaylles.</head>
               <p>ANd for to remedy the great derthe and dyfordre that ben in theſe our countrees of vytaylles as we vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande procedeth of engratynges that
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:18518:8"/>
ben vſed and done to the great hurtes &amp; hynderaunce of our ſubgectes and ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally of our poore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons and publyke welth of our ſayd countrees / we therfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re wyll ordeyn and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde our offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and men of lawe of our pryncypal townes of our countrees y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eche of them in his rowme reſpectyuely &amp; within .iii. monethes nexte folowynge this day do rate &amp; ſet pryſe reaſonable on all maner of vytaylles / and theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cepertes with in the ſayd tyme to ſend in to the handes of the rulers / cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyllers / and Iuges of prouynces where they haue Iuryſdyccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and they to ouer ſe and agre to the ſame as they thynke beſte / and to ſende it vnto vs or to the quene / our ſayd moſte dere and beſt beloued ſyſter by dyſcryte aduyſe of counceyll ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in to do as ſhalbe thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte moſt behouefull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Agaynſt bankeroutes.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:9"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to put remedye agaynſt bankeroutes / we haue ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and enacted that al mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chauntes men and women and all other perſones what ſo euer intermyttyng in the feate of mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaundyſe the which fraudulently or by wronge bereth away the money / wares or debtes of other marchauntes or perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be &amp; ſhall be holden &amp; reputed for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men theues / &amp; ſuche we haue proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them. And lyke wyſe all they that knoweth the fraude and abuſyon of the ſayd bankeroutes / and doth meynteyne receyue / or hydeth them where they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuged except they ſhewe and warne the chefe offycers and lawyers of the places where they ben. And in lykewyſe they that do medle in the doynges of the ſayd bankeroutes or in theyr abſence do lede the trayne of occupyenge with them by felawſhyp or otherwyſe. And ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly they that dyſſymule or fayne them ſelfe credytours of the ſayd bankeroutꝭ and that with them ſhall vſe to freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:18518:9"/>
tranſportes &amp; ſymulacyons / or in what ſo euer maner do them aſſyſt or helpe to the conueyaunce of theyr fraude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte. And al the aboue named and eche of them we haue pryuatyd fro the frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyſe / ſurete / and lyberte of all townes / boroughes / and other places pryuyleged with fraunchyſe. Alſo we ordeyne that the ſayd bankeroutꝭ: theyr helpers &amp; aſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtentes aboue declared y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; knowen for ſuch that for refuge do redra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we them in townes / boroughes or other priuyleged placꝭ what ſoeuer none exce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr goodꝭ by them thyther brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte or cauſed to be had thyther to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out without preiudyce. Albeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd townes / boroughes and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chyſed &amp; pryuyleged in other cauſes. And that the ſayd bankeroutes a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore declared and theyr complyces after that they ſhalbe knowen / taken / and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynted for ſuche as theues and robbers of the goodes of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welthe to be punyſſhed without fauoure or delay to the example of all other. And that the
<pb facs="tcp:18518:10"/>
goodes tranſported and conueyed by the ſayd bankeroutes and the felowes to be put in ſure kepyng to the behofe of the cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dytours as belongeth to reaſon. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wyues of the ſayd marchauntes that maketh bankeroutes / theyr huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge preſent or abſent haue occupyed or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynaryly or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly with marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and kepe ſhoppes eyther in byenge or fellynge to be bounde and holden for to anſwere or make good for theyr huſban<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des debtes made and contract ſyth theyr maryage. And moreouer we wyll and ordeyne that al marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes men or wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men that by cawtele or fraude to begyle theyr credytours abſent them ſelfe from our countrees by the ſpace of .xl. dayes / &amp; be warned by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn cryes at the place of theyr abydynge to retourne in to oure ſayd countrees within .xl. dayes after to content theyr credytours / that than they at the ende of ſayd .xl. laſt dayes and all bankeroutes fygytyues and theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aboue declared attaynte of the ſame as is aforeſayd to be banyſſhed for euer
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:18518:10"/>
out of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees and lordſhyppes and neuer after to retourne. And alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re all and whatſoeuer theyr bargaynes done this by ſymulacyon or cyrcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fraude to be none &amp; of no value. And we wyll that all the credytours of the ſayd bankeroutes and of the comply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and other ſo fledde to come and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon lyke to deuyde and take vpon the goodes of the ſayd bankeroutꝭ that may be recouered a marc the .li. without <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>fere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. Notwithſtandyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of the ſayd credytours chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to come afore another for to ſeaſon vpon the goodꝭ of the ſayd bankeroutes and they felawes ſo that it be in a pryuyleged place. And natwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge the cuſtomes ſtatutes / or pry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyleges of the ſayd places / yf they haue any / agaynſt the which in any wyſe we do not meane nor wyll the cauſes aboue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayde hauynge place / and as ferforth as nede ſhall be / we haue and wyll dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by theſe preſentes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of vacabondes.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:11"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touchynge Vacabon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des we wyll ordeyn that our ordynaunces laſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfyed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carde proclaymed in all our countrees ſhall be obſeruyd and the penalties enacted and ſet to be executed agaynſt the tranſgreſſours without dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſymulacyon or delay. And that no ꝑſone take ygnorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te in them to be newly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſſhed the .xv. day of the next moneth of nouembre / and from thenſe foreward from .vi. monethes to .vi. monethes tyll we haue otherwyſe ordeyned.</p>
               <p>¶And for bycauſe that <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſently the pore people encreaſe in theſe our preſent coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees in ouer greatter nombre then in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſte / &amp; that by experynce they are ſuffred all indyfferentlye to begge and aſke almeſſe many fautes and abuſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s enſueth bycauſe they gyue them ſelfe to ydleneſſe / whiche is begynnynge of all euylles leuynge therby them ſelfe &amp; chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren to do any handy crafte or other ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le wherby they myght gette theyr lyuyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge.
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:18518:11"/>
And conſequently applye them ſelfe to wretched and dampnable lyuynge &amp; theyr doughters to pouerte and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyneſſe: and to all wyckedneſſe &amp; vyces And though that they be yonge and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of body yet withdrawe they by great importunyte that that ſhuld be delt other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe to aeged / ſycke / impotent / &amp; them that be in great neceſſyte. And afore our departynge from theſe countrees to reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and ſette ordre in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welth. And ouer al that poore / ſycke / and other nedy and not able to gette theyr lyuyng may deſocoured and ſuſteyned to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure after the ordynaunce of almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god our creatoure by very loue &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte: we haue ordeyned and ſtatuted this that foloweth.</p>
               <p>FYrſte that neyther ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> put them ſelfe to aſke or gette al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe be nyghte nor day / openly / nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynly / couertly / nor ſecretly / in churches or ſtretes / in howſes nor before them in any maner whatſoeuer vpon
<pb facs="tcp:18518:12"/>
payn in doyng the contrary for the fyrſte tyme to be enpryſoned with breed and water at the dyſcreſſyon of our offycers and Iuſtyces / men of lawe or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones that ſhall haue charge of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent acte where as it happeneth. For the ſeconde tyme at the dyſcreſſyon aforeſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. Except fro this and reſerued the rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous man / dyent perſones / pryſoners / and Lazars whiche maye gette theyr al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe in theyr accuſtomed maner. The ſayde Lazars to haue theyr hattes and wyde longe clokes and other tokens as they oughte. On condycyon that whan they make theyr water they to go from the people as farre as they maye or can on payne to be punyſſhed as it is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde with breed and water.</p>
               <p>ALſo that no ſtraungers forayns ſhall demaunde almeſſe on lyke payn and correccyon. Sauf them that be honeſt and not wont to brycke &amp; lewtre paſſynge theyr way by pylgry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or other deuout way may lodge at
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:18518:12"/>
hoſpytalles and maſondews one nyght onely vpon payne aforeſayde. And to be receyued by the mayſters or mayſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſayde hoſpytalles they ſhall be bounde to recouer and preſente them ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fro the offycers or deputyes at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daytyng of the charyte of the places whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re they wolde lodge.</p>
               <p>ANd that no poore folke ſhal paſſe fro town to town or fro vyllage to vyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lage for to dwell or take reſydence vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyke payne. But yf by chaunce of warre of flodes myſchefe of fyre or other incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenyence they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to pouerte / and that duely they make certyfycate to them may be mynyſtred and alowed lodgyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge or howſe. And otherwyſe not. And as for poore people nowe beynge in our ſayde countrees and haue ben reſydent one yere they may abyde in the ſame eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te as they be &amp; haue part of the almeſſes that ben or ſhall be ordeyned without go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge to begge openly or ſecretly as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boueſayde.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:13"/>aLſo that eche of them ſhal kepe theyr chyldren great and ſmall from beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge or aſkynge of almeſſe vpon pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne aforeſayd. And the ſayde chyldren to be correct with roddes and otherwyſe at the dyſcreſyon of the ſayd offycers or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lawe of the places where they come.</p>
               <p>¶ And to take all the offenders of oure ſayde ordynaunces and deffences afore ſayde there ſhall be ordeyned and depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in euery towne and vyllage by the offycers and men of lawe / one or two ſergeau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ or mo yf nede be after the byg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the places.</p>
               <p>¶ And to the ſuſtentenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of pore ſeke and other nedye perſones not able to get theyr lyuynge / beynge reſydent or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in townes or vyllagꝭ of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees / we ordeyn that all the charytees tables of poore hoſpitalles: brotherhedes and other that haue obytes and diſtrybu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyons of prebendes and almeſſes be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn purce to be dealed to poore
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:18518:13"/>
people / by the abuyſe of the mayſters &amp; rulers of the ſayd tables of poore hoſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles and brotherhedes / with them that the offycers and men of lawe in euery towne / paryſſhe / or vyllage ſhall depu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt to the behoufe of the chary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te in the maner hereafter declared / Sauf that the almeſſes founded for ſpyrytuall perſones as mandyentes and other ſhall be deuyded at the ordre of the founders.</p>
               <p>ALſo from henſforewarde in euery pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſſhe churche of the townes &amp; vylla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of our countrees ſhall be ſet tronckes and blockes to put in the ſecret almeſſe of good people. And the ſaid blockꝭ and tronckes to be ſhet with thre keyes of the whiche the paryſſhe preeſt ſhal haue one the men of law one / &amp; the thyrde to hym or them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to deale the ſaid almeſſe / for to take out the ſayd money that they fynde there whan they thyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſt tyme. And moreouer there ſhal be de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puted in euery paryſſhe churche by the of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycers and men of lawe there an honeſte
<pb facs="tcp:18518:14"/>
man or two to gather for the poore folke in the ſayde churches / ones or twyſe in a weke / or as often as they ſhal ſe nedeful And alſo the ſayd deputyes of euery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe ſhall go once in a weke or oftener to the howſes of the dwellers &amp; aſke al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſſe for the relyef of poore people. And aſwell the ſayd deputyes that ſo gather the almeſſe as they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deale it to the pore ſhall be bounde to yelde accompte euery moneth of theyr receptꝭ: and lyenges out to the offycers / men of lawe or theyr aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſygnes in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn place in the preſence of all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wylcom thyther to here it.</p>
               <p>ANd for to rule and conduct this wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of charyte there ſhall be elect and choſen by the offycers and men of lawe of the townes and vyllages certayn per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones of the beſt eſtates or qualytes. The whiche choſen and deputed / we requyre and ordeyne that for the loue of god and perfyte charyte to accept the charge and to kepe the ordre and rule to them gyuen And that they ſo choſen and electe maye
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:18518:14"/>
take and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt a receyuour vnder them to kepe pertyculer accompte of the ſayde almeſſes and depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dentes or belongyng. And they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted ſhall or cauſe to make dylygent inquery of the nombre / eſtate / qualyte / &amp; condycyon of the poore people eche in theyr quarters / of what oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupacyon &amp; aege they be of / of theyr char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of chyldren and what gaynes they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue or may make.</p>
               <p>ANd they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery paryſſhe ſhall make or cauſe to be made regy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres / and in the ſame clerely wryte the effect of theyr inquery / that is to wyt the nombre of poore folkes in euery houſe / &amp; the porcyon of money nedefull to them a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue theyr gaynes in regarde of theyr fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culte / neceſſyte / and charge.</p>
               <p>ALſo the officers and men of lawe by the aduyſe af the chyef &amp; honeſt men / ſhall deuyſe to gather in one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe all the almeſſes of what ſorte ſo euer they be: for to deale the money wekely in
<pb facs="tcp:18518:15"/>
his paryſſhe to the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of the poore fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes at the dyſcrecion of them ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted Be it in money / brede / wood / clothynge or otherwyſe alwaye by them regarded the qualyte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyon of the ſayd poore folke. And to gyue no money to dronker<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / ydle folke / gamners / hazarders / nor other lyke. But brede / wood / clothynge / &amp; other neceſſaryes to maynteyne them i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr houſholdes. And the ſayd yll dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of theyr perſones ſhall be conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to worke &amp; to brynge theyr gaynes home to theyr howſes vpon payne to be put from the almeſſe of the ſayd purſe &amp; of other penaltie as ſhall be thought ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge.</p>
               <p>ALſo the pryſoners / ſycke folkes / and other that can not go out of theyr hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes or lodgynges / and women in chyld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſhall be vyſyted and holpen / &amp; pour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyed with the almeſſe of beddes / ſhetes and couerlyddes / of meates / fewell / and other nedes. And in lykewyſe orphans and chyldren that be foundlynges ſhall
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:18518:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:18518:16"/>
be nouryſſhed by the ſayd almeſſe.</p>
               <p>ANd that the chyldren of pore folkꝭ y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> before this preſent ordynaunce were vacabondes lyuynge by beggery / ſome of them ſhall be ſet to ſcole / and other to lerne occupacyons / or other feates / or to ſerue honeſt folkes. And they that lerne occupacyons / ſhall vpon ſondayes and holy dayes lerne theyr Pater noſter. theyr beleue / and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of the Churche of the ſcole mayſter that ſhal be therfore ordeyned / And he ſhal lede them or cauſe them to be led euery ſondaye to maſſe / to the ſermon / &amp; euenſonge. And to the ende that the ſayd chyldren may be more apte to ſerue &amp; lerne / they that ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to do the ſayd charyte ſhal pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uey them of raymentꝭ and other thyngꝭ behouefull / and to cauſe them to be clen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed from all fylthyneſſe / and heale them of all theyr diſeaſes / as ferforth as the al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſſes maye bere. And the offycers and men of lawe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſyoners to deale and ordre the ſayd dedes of chary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:18518:17"/>
as in theyr conſcyences they ſhall thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke beſte in the ſame.</p>
               <p>ANd that all the poore people lyuynge of the ſayd almeſſe and charyte haue and bere a marke vpon theyr gownes / at the ordynaunce of them ſo amytted.</p>
               <p>ALſo that all curates / and prechers in theyr Sermons and herynge of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyons in makynge of teſtamentes / &amp; orderynge of laſte wylles / to the good mayntenaunce and fortherynge of this ordynaunce and werkes of charyte ſhall do the beſte of theyr deuoure to exhorte / induce / &amp; moeue the people therto / to gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and departe with theyr goodes.</p>
               <p>¶And yf the poore folkes releued with the ſayd almeſſe do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne to the ſayd curates or prechers / or to other / that the ſayd almeſſe is not done to them duely / the ſayd curates prechers and other to ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke no lyght credence of them / but to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte them with meke wordes and ſende them to the orderers of the ſayde almeſſe
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:18518:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xv" facs="tcp:18518:18"/>
to be pourueyed as they ought to be / and who ſoeuer knoweth that the ſayd cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte and almeſſe is dealed to ſuche as it ought not to be / or that ſome perſone for ſhamefaſtneſſe or ſympleneſſe dare not dyſcouer theyr nede / they to ſhewe it to the deputyes / &amp; after informacyon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de they to be by them pourueyed.</p>
               <p>ANd we forbyd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none what ſo euer he be take on hym from henſforth to lodge any of the ſayde bryboures or ydle women beggers but one nyght oonly v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon payne to forfeyt thre carolus of gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / the thyrde to the accuſer / and the reſte to the profyte of the almes of the charyte.</p>
               <p>ALſo we defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de all them that by them ſelfe / theyr chyldren or other do perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer or receyue ꝑte of the almeſſes of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte from henſforth to go or haunte tauer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or cabarettes / or other lyke places. Nor the play at caylles / bowles / &amp; other games forboden vpon payne arbytray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Sufferynge them ſomtyme for recrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon
<pb facs="tcp:18518:19"/>
to drynke a potte of ſeruoyſe with theyr wyues ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they drynke not dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>ANd to the ende that this preſent wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of charyte may be obſeruyd &amp; kept for euer to the honour of god / and relyef of poore people we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to all our offycers and men of lawe: and them that be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to the ſayd dedes of charyte throughe all our countrees / eche of them reſpectyuely in the place of theyr admynyſtracyon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at all tymes and as often as nede ſhall be to fulfyll amplyfye and make better this preſent ordynaunce by newe ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whiche they ſhall perceyue and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we to ſerue &amp; be profytable to the welth: fortheraunce / maynteynynge / and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentacyon of the ſayd charyte.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Agaynſt dyſordynate drynkynge.</head>
               <p>COnſequently to remedye the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordynate drynkyngꝭ and dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes vſed in theſe our countrees in dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:18518:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:20"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:18518:20"/>
cabarettes / tauernes / and lodgyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges kept in by wayes out of townes / bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowes / vyllages / and hye wayes / and other places on dedycacyon dayes / feeſtꝭ and kermeſſes. And to eſchewe the ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues / manſlaughters and other incoueny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences therof procedynge / we haue ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeyned that all the feeſtes / ker<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meſſes / and dedycacyons in eche of oure ſayd countrees be kept vpon one day ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as by vs or our moſte dere and ryght welbeloued ſuſter the quene Regent in our abſence / by the aduyſe of the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours / cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyllers / and Iuges / prouyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyalles of the ſayde countrees / ſhalbe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned &amp; declared within .iiii. monethes after this day. And that the ſayd kermeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and dedycacyons ſhall laſte but one day onely / vpon payn that they and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of them that be founde &amp; kepe the ſayd kermeſſes &amp; dedecacyons longer or paſt the daye ordeyned to forfeyt as often as they do ther agaynſt .xxx. li. paryſys.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of brydales or weddynges.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:21"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>hat they that kepe bryda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in all our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees and lordſhyppes / ſhall not byd but theyr next kynſfolkes and frendes on both party<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es / to the nombre of .xx. perſones at the moſt. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the feaſt of the ſayde wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges ſhall not laſt more then the pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypall daye / and the nexte day tyll after noone / vpon payne to be forfeyted by them that do the contrary / as well they that kepeth the weddynges as they that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more nombre and be not of the nexte kynſfolke. And they that be there longer than it is ſayde / for eche one of them .xx. carolus of golde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶For byddynge of goſſeps.</head>
               <p>WE defende alſo that none of what eſtate he be of / to praye or deſyre godfathers / or godmothers to the chryſtenynge of theyr chyldren / to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue or receyue any gyft or profyte. And yf a preſent be gyuen or offred them. We de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fende
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:18518:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:18518:22"/>
them to take it. And lykewyſe we forbyd theym that ben deſyred to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers or godmothers to gyue them any thynge. On payne to forfeyt aſwell the gyuers as the receyuers / at euery tyme that they do ſo the thynge preſented &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued / and the double of the worth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of excepte it be to the chyldren of poore &amp; myſerable nedy perſons. At whoſe chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtenynge the godfathers &amp; godmothers / for goddes ſake may gyue theyr almeſſe at theyr pleaſures without myſtakynge or offence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt blynde hoſteryes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat from henſforth within our ſayd countrees and lord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyps none ſhall kepe tauer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / typelynges / or lodgyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in by placꝭ out of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn ſtretes and hygh wayes out of townes / vyllages: or hamletꝭ. On payne to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne in forfeyture .xx. carolles of golde doyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge to the contrary. And they that lodge
<pb facs="tcp:18518:23"/>
or ſhall drynke in the ſayd cabarettes by wayes to forfeyt .vi. golden carolles at euery tyme ſo doynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Tauernes to be ſhet on ſondayes.</head>
               <p>THat frohenſforth none of what eſtate or condycyon he be of preſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to ſet people in tauerne or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baret on the ſondayes / &amp; other holy day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded by the churche / nor for to drynke at hye maſſe tyme / or euen ſonge. On payne that they and euery of them / at euery tyme ſo doynge to pay amendes of .lx. grotes of the money of Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of manſlaughter by dronken folke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd for to ſet remedy to the great nombre of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlaughters do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne dayly in our ſayd countrees by dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe or vnder truſte of forgyueneſſe eaſyly to be had / we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:18518:23"/>
inſtantly requyred &amp; ordeyned to our ſayd moſte dere and ryghtbeloued ſuſter the quene / and expreſſely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to the chyef men of our pryue counceyl that at theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge they gyue not lyghter remyſſyon of homycydes nor other cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes procedynge of dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe: but to the contrary yf they may take them in dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe that hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted manſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or any other euyll dede / to punyſſhe them fyrſt for cauſe of theyr dronke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe And than for reaſon of theyr ſlaughter or other greiffes by them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out delay as they can fynde by ryght e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyte and Iuſtyce.</p>
               <p>WE wyll alſo do enact and ordeyne ryght expreſſely that they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and to admyt in oure name at the renuynge of the lawes of townes &amp; boroughes of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees that they do not moeue or ſet any ꝑſones i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the law which they know to be named or famed dronklewe &amp; cuſtomably exceſſyfe dron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers. And yf vnwares they haue amyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:18518:24"/>
any in to the lawe / that cuſtomably were dronken and after beynge in lawe perſeuereth dronklewe / In that cauſe to dyſmyſſe them of theyr offyce what euer it be for euer. The paynes and amendes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oueſayd to be vſed / the halfe to oure profyte / A quarter of the profyte to the ſhewer therof / and the other to the offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer that executeth it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Agaynſt exceſſe of aray.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Nd for to redreſſe the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate dyſordres &amp; exceſſes amonge the lyege people ſubgectes and other euyll inhabytau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of our ſayd countrees clothynges and araye to the inſupportable expence and preiudyce of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welthe. We haue ſtatuted / or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned defended and forboden by theſe preſent ſtatutes to all our lyege people be they Dukes / Prynces / Marquyſes / Erles / Banerettes / noble man or other our ſubgectꝭ / dwellers &amp; inhabytyers of
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:18518:24"/>
our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees in theſe ꝑties of what eſtate / qualyte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they be of to women as to men without any exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pcyon / the weryng and vſe of all ſortes and maners of clothes of golde / of cloth of ſyluer brocartes of golde and ſyluer / aſwell in clokes as capes / dowblettes / Ierkyns / cotes / &amp; Iackettes in ſleues or halfe ſleues or in bordures / gaderynges or maner that is more or leſſe that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe in any ſorte or it may be. And lyke wyſe all brawderyes of golde or ſyluer vpon any maner thynge that it may be.</p>
               <p>THat none of our lyeges or ſubge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes of what ſo euer eſtate qualy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te or condycyon he be may or ſhal from henſforth were gownes / ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>telles nor Iackettes of veluet or cremoſyn ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn / but oonly prynces / marquys / erles / or the knyghtes of our ordre / and lordes / banerettes of auncyent nobleneſſe: or the chyef of our pryue counceyll &amp; theyr chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren the chyef of offycers &amp; hed offycers of our howſe. In kepynge by them ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:18518:25"/>
and echone of theym certayne nombre of good horſes to the behoufe of theyr eſtate and vacacyon.</p>
               <p>NOr none of our lyeges or ſubge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes or other dwellers or inhaby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyers of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees other than the fore named may or ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter were gownes of blacke veluet / taw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny or other coloure / nor cremſoyn / but yf he kepe thre good horſes for the ſadle / wherof two of them ſhalbe. eche of them of the heyght of .xvi. palmes and a half at the leeſt. And that none but them abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue named may or ſhall frohenſforth we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re gownes of ſatyn or damaſke / but yf he holde two horſes / one at the leſt of the heyght of .xvi. palmes and a halfe.</p>
               <p>ANd ferthermore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none of what eſtate he be of mayr or ſhall were cote of veluet / ſatyn or damaſke / but yf he kepe one good horſe of the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte of .xvi. palmes and a halfe as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boueſayd. On payne to do the contrarye
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:18518:25"/>
at euery tyme ſo doynge of the confyſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the gownes and other raymentꝭ gardyngꝭ / and brawderyes that they do were agaynſt our preſent ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the countrees and places or confyſcacion of place. And beſyde penalte arbytrayre indyfferently of the value of the ſayde raymentes / gardes / or brawdrynges / &amp; the ſayd forfeyt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyſcacyon / and penal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties ſhall be the halfe to the profyte of the paryſſhe churche or other churches of the place where it is founde or had / at the or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derynge and dyſcrecyon of the Iuges / one quarter to the profyte of the brynger forth. And the other quarter to the behou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe of the offycer that executeth it.</p>
               <p>ANd in the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as is aboueſaid the women and chyldren ſhall be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led accodynge to the degre of theyr huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; fathers. And the wydowes in this behalfe ſhall remayne in theyr wydow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed and be reputed as they were in theyr huſbandes dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:26"/>ANd that they whiche haue rayme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſylkes may pourney themſelfe of other. And that they that wold were garmentes of ſylkes may pouruey them of horſes / we haue conſented and agreed that they that haue raymentes of ſylkes maye were them yf they pleaſe vnto Chryſtmaſſe day next folowyng And that they that wolde were ſylkes / may pouruey them of horſes within the ſame tyme. Prouyded alwaye and that we defend forbyd that at the ſayde feeſt of Cryſtmaſſe that they that haue no hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes as we haue ſayd ſhal not make new clothynges of ſylkes. And the tayllours ſhall not make them / but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the cheyf officer of the place it be certyfyed that he that wolde make newe garmentes of ſylke be pourueyed of horſes as it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned. To the obſeruacyon wherof we haue enacted and ordeyned that all offy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers and eche of them make dylygent vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſytacyon euery thre monethes / yf they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were ſylkes in the lymytes of theyr offy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces do kepe nombre of horſes confermal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:18518:26"/>
to the ſayd ordynaunce. And theyr vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſytacyon to be put in wrytynge by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Inuytorye of them that kepe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And they to ſend them euery thre mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethes to the quene our ſuſter. On payn of forfayture of a. C. carolles of golde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tyme that they do myſſe to be put to our vſe &amp; profyte / to the ende that our ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter the quene may knowe euery thre mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethes what nombre of horſes we maye recouer in our countrees.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶For horſes.</head>
               <p>FOr to retayne the marchaundyſe of Horſes in our countrees to the welthe &amp; profyte of many of our ſubgectes that make marchaundyſe of them / we haue defended and forfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) to all perſones be they oure ſubgectes or ſtraungers to carye any Mares out of our ſayde countrees / On payne of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytoure of the ſayde Mares / and alſo the valoure of them the halfe to our vſe One quarter to the fynder / and the other quarter to the offycer that executeth it.</p>
               <p>¶We forbyd and defende to al perſones
<pb facs="tcp:18518:27"/>
our ſubgectꝭ or ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers to bye any hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the playne countrees: &amp; to all other for to ſell them out of free fayres or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes. On payn of forfeyture of the ſaid horſes for the ſellers &amp; the valewe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the byers. In this reſerued our ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of our houſholde / and men of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce / the which for our ſeruyce and theyr rydyng may bye them in the playn countrees. And they that haue ſuche hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to ſell them to them as well as in fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fayres without offendynge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶ Agaynſt ſwerers &amp; blaſphemers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to redreſſe &amp; put remedye agaynſt blaſphemers / we haue defended al perſones to blaſpheme our lord god the vyrgyne Mary / the ſayntes or theyr names. On payne that they that forſake god / dyſauowe god / or dyſpyte hym / his mother theyr names or the ſayntꝭ: to be enpryſoned the ſpace of a
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:18518:27"/>
hole moneth in a depe dongeon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brede &amp; water. And they that ſo do blaſpheme with harde and felonous hertes / beſyde the ſayd pryſonement to haue theyr ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues perced openly vpon a ſcaffolde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out grace fauour or delay. And they that make any other vylayne othes to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhed in theyr bodyes arbytrarylye at the dyſcrecion of the Iugꝭ vnder whom the ſayde othes be made / or of hym that hath knowleg therof. And that the ſayd Iuges dyſſymule nor deffer the punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhement of blaſphemers / or fowle ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers in maner aforeſayd. On payn to be pryuate and put out of theyr offyces for euer: nor to recouer or excercyſe any other</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of mutuell frendſhyp amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſubgectes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touchynge the mutuell intellygence and amyte be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>twene our ſayd countrees and ſubgectes / the whiche we haue ꝓpoſe to our eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of our ſayd countrees in theyr aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blynge
<pb facs="tcp:18518:28"/>
laſt with vs. Conſyderyng that in the ſayd intellygence confederacyons and good amytees co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyſteth &amp; dependeth chyefly the force / the ſurete / and reſt / and in effect the welth of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynte of the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees. We them requyred and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne moſt certaynly. And vpon as mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che as they deſyre to obey vs and do vs pleaſure and for theyr owne welth / ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; reſt / as they ben all vnder vs theyr oonly prynce / naturall and ſoueraygne lorde / that lykewyſe they loue eche other and haue mutuell good and true intelly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence and loue that they conuerſe &amp; hau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t louyngly one with another / &amp; to entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medle and vſe togyther in all thynges / wherof the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytees more in one cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie than in the other and as neyghbours frendes / and ſubgectes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtytued vnder one prynce ben bounden &amp; ought to do. And that they aſſyſt / &amp; helpe eche other in theyr mutuell defence / ſurete and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quylyte. ¶And yf that occaſyon of dyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycult chaunce betwene any of the ſayd countrees that it be auoyded louyngly a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monge
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:18518:28"/>
them yf it maye be. yf not / with the meanes of the gouernours of the ſaid countrees echone to his power or where nede ſhalbe by interuencyon of our ſayd ryghte dere and well beloued ſuſter the quene without fygure of proceſſe. And this doynge to vs ſhalbe ryght agreable And we ſhall kepe them / defende / &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue from all empryſes / forces vyolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / outrages / &amp; greues as a good prynce naturall / and ſouerayn lord ought to do for his true obeyers / countrees / and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gectes. And we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde and ryght ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſely ordeyne oure wel beloued fyege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men the chyef preſedent and men of our pryue counceyll / to the preſedent and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our great counceyll. To the chauncel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll in Brabant To the gouernour and men of our coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyll at Luxembourg. To the preſedent and men of our counceyll in Flaundres To the gouernour and men of our coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyll in Artoys. To the hygh bayllyf of Haynau &amp; men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyl at Mons. Lyeftenaunt and men of our counceyll
<pb facs="tcp:18518:29"/>
in Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / zellande / and fryſe. Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour / preſedent and men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll at Namur. Lyeftenaunt / preſedent and men of our counceyll at Vtrecht. To the gouernour Doneryſſel. To the rent may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters of Beweſt / &amp; Beorſterſchelt in zel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. To the gouernour of the yle of Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uay &amp; Orchyes. To the prouoſt le conte at Valenciennes. And to Leſconttete of Malynes and to all oure other offycers and Iuſtyces that they take hede and ſe that our ſayd ordynaunces ſtatutes / edy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es / and defences to be publyſſhed / and proclayme Zechone in theyr quarters and lymytes of theyr Iuryſdyctions / and ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynyſtracyons the .xv. day of the next moneth of Nouembre / and in our name ryght ſtrayghtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to all our ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gectes / habytauntes and conuerſyng in our ſayd countrees / that our ſaid ſtatute edyctes / &amp; defencꝭ be kept &amp; holde i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly without gaynſayng dyrectly or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycetly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner whatſoeuer. &amp; to the ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruynge of the ſayd ſtatutes / edyctes / &amp; defences they do procede and cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cede
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:18518:29"/>
eche to his power reſpectyuely. And in theyr lymytes of theyr Iuryſdyccions agaynſt the tranſgreſſoures of the ſame by the execucyons of the penalties therto appoſed reſpectyuely without fauour ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mulacyon / grace / or delay. For ſo is our pleaſure. In wytneſſe wherof we haue cauſed to ſet our ſeale to theſe preſentes.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Gyuen at our towne of Bruxelles <date>the .vii. day of Octobre / the yere of grace .M.v.L.xxxi. the ſeconde of our empyre / &amp; of regnes of ſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / and bothe the Cycylles and other: the .xvi.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>Thus ſubſcrybed By the Emperoure in his counceyll. And ſygned of the ſecretarye Dublioul.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:18518:30"/>
               <head>¶Agaynſt the Lutherayns. ¶By the Emperour.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O our wel beloued lyeges the Chaunceller and men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll of Braba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gretynge &amp; dyſeccyon.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>For to remedy and pouruey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the Abuſyons &amp; errours of Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyn Luther &amp; other auctoures and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued heretykes and theyr dyſcyples / ſecta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours / and imitatours adherentes and complyces which haue heretofore perfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced and wylled to ſowe theyr hereſyes in our countrees in theſe partyes to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudyce of the Chryſten fayth / of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes / Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes / and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces of our mother holy Churche. We therfore haue longe ſythen requyred our holy father the Pope / to depute and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytte inquyſytours in our ſayd coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees. And alſo we haue decerned &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpede. Fyrſte in our Imperyall cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Wormes / and ſythen in other placꝭ our Lettres of placarde conteynynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:18518:30"/>
ſtatutes and ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with penalties agaynſt the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere imitatoure of Martyn Luther / or of his adherentes / &amp; complyces. And ſythen in the moneth of Octobre of the yere .M.v.L.xxix. laſt paſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to our knowle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the abuſyons &amp; errours of the ſayd Martyn Luther / his imitatours &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and other dampnable ſectꝭ aſwell by the conuerſacyon of ſome of them in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees / as that many of euyll her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and wyll do not exteme or doubte the paynes oppoſed in our ſayd ordynauncꝭ haue publyſſhed and multyplyed them in our countrees. We to remedy the ſame by the aduyſe of the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellers of our or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre &amp; of the chyef men of our pryue coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyll and many other good perſones ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uocate and aſſembled: with great and rype deleberacion of the late / &amp; than lyuynge our moſte dere / and ryght wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued lady &amp; aunte the Archeducheſſe of Auſtryche regent for vs who god aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle ſhuld haue made and ordeyned mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re rygorous ſtatutes and ordynaunces a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:18518:31"/>
the abuſyons of our fayth / and ordres of the churche as it appereth in the lettres of our placarde gyuen in our tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of Bruxcelles the .xiiii. day of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / the yere .M.v.L.xxix. &amp; publyſſhed the ſame i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres. but neuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theleſſe it is yet agayne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege that the ſaid Martyn Luther &amp; other auctours reproued: &amp; their ſectatours i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatours &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pſyces do ꝑforce them more &amp; more to publyſſhe ſowe &amp; inprynt theyr actours &amp; abuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree. De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyryng to put remedy we hauyng agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne thaduyſe of men of eſtate of all oure ſayde countrees and counceylles prouyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyalles by the aduyſe of the chauncellers of our ordre / and of the chyef of our pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll to the honour of god our crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure / to the mayntenaunce of the holye fayth / of the ſacramentes / ſtatutes / ordy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunces / and conſtytucyons of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy churche agayne of newe ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; ordeyned the poyntes and artycles folowynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:18518:31"/>FYrſte that no perſon nor perſones of what nacyon eſtate or condy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon he or they be from henſforthe prynt or wryte / bye or ſell / gyue / rede / ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe / or reteyne vnder hym / or receyue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / inſtructe or teche / ſuſteyne / or defend co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune / or dyſpute / openly or ſecretly / or kepe conuentycles or aſſembles of the bokes / wrytynges / or doctrynes / or any of them made or ſhall be made by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn Luther. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wykelyf. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hus. Marcillius de paduay. Ecolampadine. Olricus / zwyngly. Philippus mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Franciſcus lamberti. Iohannes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merani. Ottho bruſſi. Iuſtus Ione. Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hannes pupery / and Gorchianus / or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther auctours of theyr ſecte / or of other ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes of heryſyes errours or abuſyons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of the churche. Nor alſo the doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of theyr adherentes / fautours / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyces. Nor the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes enpryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by Adryan de bargie. Chryſtoferus de Raymundia / and Iohan<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es zell. full of Lutherayn heryſyes or other and for ſuche reproued and condempned by the
<pb facs="tcp:18518:32"/>
faculte of theologyens in the vnyuerſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of Couayn. Nor lykewyſe any bokes that ſyth .x. yeres hytherto haue ben wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten or imprynted without ſhewynge the names of the auctours / prynters or wry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters / nor the tyme and places / when they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pyled wryten or prynted. Nor al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / the goſpellꝭ / epyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / ꝓphetyes nor other what ſoeuer bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes in frenche or Thyriz hauynge prefa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces / or prologues / apoſtylles or gloſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teynynge or touchynge any doctryne / or errour or any wyſe derogaunte or repug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge contrary to the chryſten fayth / to the ſacramentes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god and of the churche or to the doctryne of the ſame. Nor lyke wyſe to paynt por<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tray or cauſe to be paynted portrayed / to haue / holde / or kepe any ymages / portra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turys / payntynges / or opprobryous and dyſpyteful fygures of god of the blyſſed vyrgyn Mary / or of ſayntes. Or to bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke marre / or deface the ymagꝭ / or portray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures made to the remembraunce and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure of god / of the vyrgyn Mary / or
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:18518:32"/>
the ſaynes approued of the churche. And moreouer that none of what eſtate that he be of preſume to talke or dyſpute of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcrypture in doubtfull maters or diffy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyle / but yf they be ryght well famed &amp; approued Theologyens by famous v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyuerſyties. On payne to them that do the contrary of confyſcacyon of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyes without grace / reſpyte / or delaye. That is to wyt of them that here before haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted any errour and beyng ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iured and ben fallen therin agayne to be executed by fyre. And other / as men by ſwerde. and the woman by the pyt / and theyr hedes ſet there aboute / in example of other / &amp; the forfeyture of theyr goodes or of place.</p>
               <p>ANd that none of what ſoeuer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon kynde / or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyon preſume or auaunce them from henſforthe to tranſlate / wryte / or prynte / plane / or bynde within our ſayd countree of Bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bant any bokes / quyres / or what ſoeuer doctrynes of holy wryt in frenche / or thy
<pb facs="tcp:18518:33"/>
riz / nor in other ſpeche than laten. Nor al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo to cauſe to make / nor to brynge or cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe to brynge in to our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees / any of the ſayde bokes / or other / tranſlated / wryten / or enprynted in other countrees without the leue of the ordynary / or of you chaunceller and men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyl in the ſayd countrees / and your approba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of the ſayde bokes quayres or wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges.</p>
               <p>ANd that none preſume frohenſforth to prynte or wryte / or cauſe to prynte or wryte any newe bokes / quayers / or volumes thoughe they be not compoſed by Martyn Luther / or by them afore na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or other ſuſpect &amp; reproued auctours or any of them / and that the ſayd bokes or wrytynges be no treatye of any hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycall mater / erronyous / or ſuſpecte / but that the ſayd bokes quyers / or volumes be eccleſiaſtycall maters tyll the ordyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry or his deputye haue vyſyted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued them. And that the ſayd prynter or wryter neyther for to prynt nor wryte
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:18518:33"/>
them: but yf they haue for the ſame obtey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned our lettres patentꝭ of graunt &amp; lycen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce vpon payne of doynge the contrarye without grace or reſpyte vpon a ſcaffol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to be marked with a hote yren in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a croſſe ſo ſharply that it may not be put a ware / or to haue one iye put out or one hande out of / at the dyſcrecyon of the Iuge / to the regarde of myſuſynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> brekynge of the ſayd ordynaunces</p>
               <p>WE alſo ordeyn and ſtatute for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement that no hoſt nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſſe nor other perſones / of what nacyon eſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycion they be of wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyngly lodge receyue fauour or ſuſteyn any heretykes or abuſers of the fayth of the ſacramentes and ordynaunces of the church: or that hath done agaynſt our ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutes &amp; ordynaunces. And that all they that haue lodged them / receyued / fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red / or ſuſteyned / knowynge them to be ſuche / and that they do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewe in theyr falſe errours to ſhewe whiche they be / (within .xv. dayes next folowynge the
<pb facs="tcp:18518:34"/>
publycacion of theſe preſentes) to the chy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ef offycers of the nexte good towne of theyr abydynge. On payne of faylynge therof of forfeyture and loſſe of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyes without reſpyte / &amp; alſo theyr i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable goodes of confyſcacyons of theyr mouables.</p>
               <p>ANd that all they that here before ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ben / or hereafter ſhal be attaynt of heryſye or abuſynge of the fayth or ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes / or conſtytucyons and ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of the churche ſhal not from henſforth company nor talke one with an other of maters defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the churche. On pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of confyſcacyon of theyr bodyes and goodes lyeng in countre or terrytory / of theyr mouables.</p>
               <p>¶That none attaynt or by informacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on precedent vehemently ſuſpect of here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye or errour in the fayth or of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and ordynaunces of the churche / ſhall not excercyſe / haue / nor kepe in our ſayd countree of Brabant / of vs of our lyeges / or other perſones. Nor in townes
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:18518:34"/>
or other places of our ſayde countre any honourable eſtate what ſoeuer nor be of our counceylles in any townes. And de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende our offycers &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſſioners at the renewyng of the lawes of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trees to admyt them to ſhyrefſhyp or any other maner eſtate or rowme.</p>
               <p>ANd deſyrynge to pouruey for the kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welege of hereſyes / errours / and abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyons agaynſt the catholyke faythe / the ſacramentes and ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / whiche be or may be in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre / we accorde and ordeyne by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes / to them that do name and ſhewe them / or to our Iuſtycꝭ and offycers as it ſhal be ſeen. They that ben accuſed to be duely attaynt and conuycte. That is to wyt of eche of them that do not excede C. li. of grotes / money of Flaundres for one tyme. And yf they excede the ſayde. C. li. of grotes / we accorde and ordeyne that ouer and aboue the halfe of the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. C. li. of grotes / the ſayd ſhewers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers or accuſers to haue the .x. penye of
<pb facs="tcp:18518:35"/>
the goodes / &amp; that that is excedynge the coſtes and expenſes in the ſuyt of Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce prealably deduct of the ſayde goodes / we wyll that to the honoure of god it be beſtowed in werkes of pyte &amp; mercy.</p>
               <p>WE ordeyne alſo &amp; enact by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and wyll that our offycers and other tofore whom the domy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours of any hereſyes / errours / or abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyons of the fayth / of the ſacramentes or prceptes of god / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtytucyons of the churche / or the brekynge of our preſent or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynaunces / ſhall come / ſo ferforthe that by preſedent informacyon accuſynge or otherwyſe theyr fautꝭ do appere / that dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygently agaynſt them they do procede / and put them in cauſe before our truſtye &amp; welbeloued counceyllers in our chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cery of Brabant / mayſter Adolf vanð noot doctour / and mayſter Ioſſe vanð<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duſſe lycenciat in the droytes. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che duely informed by theyr wyt / prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce lernynge / ryghtwyſneſſe &amp; dylygence we haue deputed and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted by theſe
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:18518:35"/>
preſentes / and gyue them power / aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte and ſpecyall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement to exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myne and knowe the ſayd cauſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out longe fygure of proceſſe / and as ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtancyally and wel as by reaſon &amp; equy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te may be done. And ryght ex<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſſely we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de them that in gyuyng theyr ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tences and appoyntementes agaynſt all and euery of them that ſhal be attaynt &amp; conuyct for doynge contrary to theſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces or any artycle of them / and to haue them in before our chaunceller &amp; other of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll / and there wel vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den to ordeyne as ye ſhall thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke beſt to be done with reaſon.</p>
               <p>ANd yf the offycers or other to whom the ſayd denouncers or accuſers were adreſſed be neclyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to procede agaynſt them that be denounced to them by prece<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dent informacion or otherwyſe duely as it is ſayde not cauſynge the ſentences as they haue obteyned to be pryuate of their offyces and eſtates and arbytrary correc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions. And that the ſayd denou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cers may
<pb facs="tcp:18518:36"/>
recouer theyr ryghte of denouncyacyon vpon the goodes of our ſayd offycers or other neclygent in theyr deuoure / at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oyſe of the ſayd denouncers.</p>
               <p>ANd for to bynde our offycers &amp; other to whom the deuouncers do come / &amp; the whiche bycauſe of theyr eſtate and by theſe preſentes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted to procede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them that ben accuſed of hereſye or abuſyon of the fayth / or of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes &amp; ordynaunces of the churche / or brekynge of our preſent ſtatutes actes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to do theyr deuoure. we haue ſtatuted &amp; ordeyned that our ſayde offycers and other to whom this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon adreſſeth to ſende vs euery thre mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nethes / and in our abſence to our ryght dere &amp; welbeloued ſuſter the quene play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne declaracyon of the accuſacyons &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncyacyons to them made of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd maters / and of theyr procedynges / deuours and dylygences agaynſt theym that haue be denounced or accuſed. On payn yf they be neclyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of loſſe of theyr
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:18518:36"/>
offyces / eſtates / and payne arbytrary.</p>
               <p>ANd we ordeyn moſte expreſſely that the aboueſayd ordynaunces / ſtatutes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / be publyſſhed the xv. day of the next moneth of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre in euery place of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre &amp; duchy of Brabant / where proclamacyons are wont to be publyſſhed. And fro that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me euery .vi. moneth tyll by vs is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe ordeyned / And by vs it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely and moſte ſtraytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded and defended that none preſume to do there a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt. And for the obſeruynge &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teynynge of the ſayd ordynaunces &amp; ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes to ꝓcede agaynſt the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſours Alſo agaynſt our offycers / Iuſtyces / &amp; other that ben neclygent in doynge theyr deuour by reall execucyon of the paynes &amp; forfeytures in them appoſed withoute delay or ſymulacyon. This for to do we gyue you power &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt you auctoryte and ſpecyall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. And com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde to all our Iuges / offycers / and ſubgectes that ſo do theyr deputyes &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:18518:37"/>
of them &amp; theyr ſubſtytutes dylygent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to entende and obey any oppoſycyon or appellacyon made or to be made not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witſtandynge / for thus it pleaſeth vs.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Gyuen in our towne of Bruxcelles <date>the vii. daye of Octobre / the yere .M.v.C.xxxi.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>Thus ſubſcrybed. By the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reour in his counceyll / And ſygned by the ſecretary Dublioul.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>¶Of the acte for Coyne. By the Emperour.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O our truſty and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Chaunceller &amp; men of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyll in Brabant gretynge and dyleccyon.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>It is gyuen vs to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſyth our retourne in to theſe our preſent countrees that the ordynaunce vpon the feate of Coyne of moneyes made the .x. day of Decembre / the yere .xvi. laſt paſt to begyn the fyrſte daye of Marche than folowyng the ſayd yere. The whiche or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynaunce in the aduyſe of the eſtates / &amp;
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:18518:37"/>
great nombre of notable and good perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of our countrees expert in the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of featꝭ of money / of the generalles or wardens of the ſayd moneyes / of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our prouyncall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceylles and of our receptes with great and rype delyberacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the late our ryght dere &amp; welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Lady and aunte tharcheducheſſe of Auſtryce. &amp;c. than regent for vs in our ſayd countrees / whom god aſſolue. For the moſt welth / vtylyte / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte / and profyte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welth of our ſayde countrees and ſubgectes. we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; made / And the ſame than &amp; ſythen often cauſed to be proclaymed in all our countrees (not beynge obſerued) And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyuers pens of golde and ſyluer by the ſayde ordynaunce declared byllyon we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re brought in to our ſayd countrees that the pens of golde and ſyluer of our forge and other prynces by the ſayd ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce valued (by theyr weyght) to be alow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed as they be yet without weyeng / and all at a heygher pryce than they be valu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed. And that the good pens of golde and
<pb facs="tcp:18518:38"/>
ſyluer of our forge and of other prynces by our ſayd ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce enualued hauyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge theyr weyght be tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſported i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge countrees and from the ſayd ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge countrees ſmal pens of lytell value ben brought in to our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees / by people ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge theyr partyculer profyte and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the great hynderaunce and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doyng of our ſayd countrees / ſubgectes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myn welth of the ſame (the which for the moſte parte lyeth in the feate and ordre of the money) and to the preiudyce of our hyghneſſe / auctoryte / ſygnoury &amp; obeyſaunce / and in dyſeſtymacyon of our ordynaunces / whiche is a thyng not to beleft deſyryng remedy / we vpon the ſame agayne hath had aduyſe of the eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of our ſayde countrees / and of many notable perſones knowlegynge in featꝭ of money / the mayſters of our moneys &amp; myntes / the chyef men of our prouyncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all counceylles / and of the accomptes of our ſayde countrees / with the knyghtes of oure ordre, and the chyef of our pryue counceyll and of our ſayd treaſours / for
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:18518:39"/>
the ſame aſſembled: after many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyons vpon &amp; for the ſame with great and rype delyberacyon / for the conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon of our hyghneſſe / auctoryte / and obeyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / &amp; for the more euydent welth vtylyte / profyte / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myn welth of our ſayde countrees and ſubgectes / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fermacyon of our ſayd laſt ordynaunce in the feate of moneyes / we haue of new ſtatuted and ordeyned this that foloweth.</p>
               <p>FYrſt that accordynge to our ſayde laſt ordynaunce begon the .x. day of Marche the yere .xxvi. laſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. The pens of gold and ſyluer hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpecyfyed / and declared redely / &amp; frohenſforth ſhalbe alowed / and currau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in our ſaid countrees in theſe partyes at ſuche weyght &amp; pryce and in maner as it foloweth.</p>
               <p>That is to wyt. ⁂</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:40"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ryall of fyne golde of our newe forge of .xlvi. in the marke / at the pryce of .lx. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The halfe ryall of .lxx. pycce / and halfe quarter in the marke at .xxx. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The floryn karolus of .lxxx. and .iiii. in the marke at .xx. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The golden flece of golde of .liii.z. in the marke at .l.z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The great ryall of Auſtryche of .xv. in the marke at .viii. floryns karolus .xi. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The halfe and quarter of the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The noble Henricus of .xxxvi. in the marke / at .iii. floryns karolus .xii.z. pat.</p>
               <p>¶The halfe noble &amp; quarter accordyng.</p>
               <p>¶The noble of Flaundres of .xxxvi. in the marke / at .iii. floryns karolus .xii. z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The halfe and quarter accordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The aungell noble of Englande of .xlviii. in the marke / at .lvii. pattars.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:18518:38"/>¶The halfe after the rate accordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The lyon of golde of .lix. in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / at .xliiii. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The .ii. thyrde partes: and the .iii. parte of them accordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The rydder of golde / the ducates of ſpayne / of portugale / and other lyke du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates of .lxx. in the marke. The ducates of Hungrye of .lxix. in the marke / at .xxxix. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The halfe accordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The caſtyllyon of fyne golde of .liii. z. in the marke / at .li. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The ducate of Ytaly / &amp; the ſalute of .lxxii. in the marke / at .xxxviii. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The two ꝑtes of the ſalut accordyng.</p>
               <p>¶The floryns with ſaynt Andrewes croſſe of .lxxiiii. in the marke / at .xxix. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The floryns of Guyllermꝰ of .lxxii. in the marke / at .xxix. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The ſchutkyns of .lxxiii. in the marke at .xxxv. z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The Iohannes of .lxxiii. in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / at .xxv. pattars.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18518:39"/>¶The floryns Philippus forged i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres ſyth the yere M. iiii. L. lxxxxvii of .lxxiiii. in the marke / at .xxv. pattars</p>
               <p>¶The halfe of them accordynge.</p>
               <p>¶The Philippus clynkarte of .lxxvi. in the marke / at .xxi. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The Peter of louayn of .lxxvi. in the marke / at .xxvi. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The fredericus and floryns of bauyce of .lxxviii. i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the marke / at .xx. z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The floryn arnoldꝰ of .lxxxxii. in the marke / at .xiiii. z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The Poſtulat of burbon / and with a cat of .lxxxi. in the marke / at .xvi. z. pat.</p>
               <p>¶The floryns of vtryght Dauyd and none other at .lxxvi. in the marke / at .xxiiii. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The floryng golde of Almayn who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe fygures be prynted and none other of lxxv. in the marke / at .xxviii. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The olde ſcutes of Fraunce with the crown of .lxxii. i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the marke / at .xxxv. z. pattars.</p>
               <p>¶The franciſcus crownes of golde coy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by the kynge now beynge of .lxx. in
<pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:18518:41"/>
the marke &amp; other lyke / at .xxxvi. patts.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Alwayes at two grotes of Flaundres the pattart.</head>
                  <p>¶And the ſayd pens or pyeces of gold &amp; none other ſhall haue cours in our ſayde countrees / at the pryce &amp; weyght aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd with the helpe of a Deuſken on eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry pyece of golde. All in maner declared in thordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the yere .M. v. L. xx.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of ſyluer and other coynes.</head>
                  <p>THe double karolus of fyne ſyluer that be now coyned in our money<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in theſe partyes ſhal be currau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in money of Flaundres / at .vi. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The ſyngle of the ſame / at .iii. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The pattars that were coyned here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / and they that be coyned now in our ſayd money / at .ii. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The great ryall of ſyluer / at .xii. grotꝭ The golden flece of ſyluer / at .vi. grotes</p>
                  <p>¶The reall of ſyluer with the armes of Spayne / at .vi. z. grotes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18518:42"/>¶The double pattars / at .iiii. groies.</p>
                  <p>¶The doubles with two gryffons &amp; .ii. helmets with the crowne / at .v.z. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The half &amp; quarter aft the rate of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>¶The doubles with two lyons: the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynoys &amp; them of Burbon / at .iiii. z. grotꝭ</p>
                  <p>¶The ſyngle of them / at .ii. grotes / and vnmytes.</p>
                  <p>¶The doubles Phylyps / and karolus of Burgoyn / at .v. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The ſyngle of the ſame accordynge.</p>
                  <p>¶The Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes braſſe pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyngꝭ / at .iii. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The phylyppꝰ of Namur / at .ii. grotꝭ</p>
                  <p>¶The double pattart forged at luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg / at .iii.z. grotes.</p>
                  <p>¶The ſyngle of them after the rate.</p>
                  <p>AS touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the douzains / pattars and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blankes of fraunce ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge the chaungynge &amp; enpayryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge ſyth our laſt ordynaunce / in the feate or act of moneyes. And that ſome grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blankes by the aſſay / that we haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to make they be founde but at the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:18518:40"/>
of .ix. pens / other but .vii. other but vi. other but .v. and other but .iiii pens tourneys. And therfore it is not veray poſſyble to value them Iuſtly. And yf they were valued the poore ſymple peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple coude not knowe them. We haue for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boden and defended in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres
the cours of the ſayde pattars and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t blankes and all whyte money of fraun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce tyll that oure ryght dere and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brother and coſyn the kynge of frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and we haue agreed of the pre / alloy &amp; of the pryce &amp; valuacyon of oure money<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es / or that otherwyſe by vs be ordeyned.</p>
                  <p>ANd the grotes / halfe grotes / gigotz / lytell pens &amp; other pens of Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / and other pens / half pens / courtes / &amp; my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / forged in our moneyes ſhal haue con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe in our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees as they are wont. And it is to wyt that with the ſayd half gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and other money vnder them no pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes ſhal be made / or courſe of rentes of marchaundyſes or other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18518:41"/>aNd as for other pens of golde or ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer not heretofore valued (of what coyne or for ſoeuer they be) we haue decla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red them byllyon and forbyd the alow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce / of them in theſe our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres at any pryce / nor by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutacyon nor ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunge of any wares / or moneyes gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or ſyluer. On payne of forfeyture of the ſayd pens &amp; of .l. floryns of golde ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus for the fyrſte tyme: For the ſeconde tyme / of the ſayd pens and a. L. karolus And for the thyrde of the ſayd pens and of .CC. karolus or other arbytrary pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalte at the dyſcrecyon of the Iuges / af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the xigence of the caſe and the faculte of the offenders / Yf it be not by the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the exchaungers ordeyned by the ſayd generalles in our ſayde countrees. The whiche exchaungers ſhall be boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to gyue the value and cut them &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them to our mynte to be molten / On the payne hereafter declared.</p>
                  <p>ANd that our preſent ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce may be the better kept / and that our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:18518:42"/>
and ſubgectes / &amp; them that be there reſydent or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſaunt be dyſcharged of the auauntagyous moneyes of golde &amp; ſyluer by this preſent acte declared bylly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / we ordeyn that the generalles of our ſaid moneyes within the .xv. day of No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uembre that our ordynaunce ſhal be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claymed or ſoone after go forthwith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyntly or ſeuerally to all the chyef and other townes / boroughes / and fraunchy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of our ſayd countrees where as nede ſhall be. And by the aduyſe of the offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and men of lawe therfore pouruey on our parte / yf they haue not done it all<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redy / And yf they had / and theyr prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon be not obſerued of exchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers able folke and conuenyent for to bye the ſaid pens of golde and ſyluer dyffended / and gyuynge to them that hath them the pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and value / cut them in the receyuynge and bere them to our myntes / ſo that the ſayd exchaungers haue reaſonable ſala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of it / that is to wytte thre pattars / for euery .li. of grotes money of Flaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres of the metall of byllyon golde or ſyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:18518:43"/>
that they do chaunge / more or leſſe af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the inſtruccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that the ſayd general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les do gyue to the ſayde chaungers. And the ſayd chaungers at theyr inſtruccyon to make ſolempne othe in the handes of the ſayd generalles / or one of them in the preſence of the chyef offycer and men of lawe there as they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted inuyola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly to kepe theyr inſtruccyon. On payne of loſſe of theyr offyces / &amp; to be proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnworthy for euer to bete offyce in our ſaid countrees and of .vi. C. floryns karolus of golde / and other payne arby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
                  <p>FErthermore we forbyd the ſayde exchaungers nor other of what eſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dycyon ſoeuer they be to try the heuy pens of gold or ſyluer for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged in our moneyes nor other valued by this preſent ordynaunce from the lyghte pens for theyr aduauntage. On payne for euery tyme ſo doyng eche of them .vi C. floryns karolus / and to be pryuate of theyr rowme and offyces beſyde pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltye
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:18518:43"/>
arbytrary. And other that be no chaungers nor our offycers. On payne of an .C. karolus and penalte at the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecyon of the Iuges.</p>
                  <p>ALſo to eſchewe and take away the oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſyon of the reyſyng and enpayryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of moneyes whiche men ſay is proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the calculacyon and rekenyng by poundes ſolz and pens of grotes money<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of Flaundres or Brabant / whiche is vſed in moſte parte of the chyef cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees in theſe partyes / we do ordeyn and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cte by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement that frohenſforth al our demaynes tayllyages our mylles medowes / and woodes. Our rentes &amp; other goodes. Thoſe of prelates &amp; other men of the churche. Alſo of our ſeruaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and other of our countrees and lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppes of what eſtate that they be. All contractes of marchaundyſes / hyrynge of goodes / of ſeruaantes / and in effecte all conuenauntes wherof ſo euer it be / be made / payde / and fulfyllyd with flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryns karolus of golde of true weyght &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18518:44"/>
alloy of oure newe coyne at the pryce of .xx. pattars the karolus / or of other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney golde or ſyluer valued after the rate as aboueſayde. And that yf any conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of what ſoeuer it be ſyth the fyrſt daye of Marche the yere .xxvi. laſt / that our ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the .x. daye of Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre in the ſayd yere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fermed to the ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the yere .xx. is begon were made at poundꝭ of grotes of flaundres and Bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bant. we wyll and ordeyn that albeit in the ſayd caſe any be or ſhal be bounde to paye for the fulfyllynge of ſuche conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes .vi. floryns karolus gold for the pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of grotꝭ of flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dres .iiii. for the .li. of grotes of Brabant &amp; one karolus of gold for euery .li. of .xl. grotes. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe yf by contractes of rentes or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe precedynge the ſayde fyrſte day of Marche the yere .xxvi. laſt it were other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe appoynted ſuche contractes maye be fulfylled after theyr tenoure / and of the wrytynges that ben made and expedyed. ⸫ ⸫ ⸫</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:18518:44"/>MOreouer for ſurete of the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon of the ſayde ordynaunce we haue ordeyned that all ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of condempnacyons / of penaltyes / and amendes (that ſhalbe made and ren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our pryue / great / and other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceylles. Alſo ouer all our Iugꝭ / offycers and men of lawe of townes more and leſſe or other places of our ſayd countres as well by the Iuges and offycers / of prelates / of our ſeruauntes / noble / and other folkes / hauynge Iuryſdyccyon in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres) be made with karolus of golde of our ſayde money / &amp; be payde in karolus at the pryce of .xx. pattars or in other money valued after the rate.</p>
                  <p>And alſo that the wages &amp; pencyons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we gyue or ſhall gyue from henſforth to al our pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyonaryes / to them of our houſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde and all our offycers be compted &amp; payde in karolus of golde. And that in lykewyſe it be done by folke of all eſtatꝭ in our countrees and ſygnoryes. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all lyterages that from that day forwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſhalbe ſped in al our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees in who<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
<pb facs="tcp:18518:45"/>
name and by whome it be in coyne of gold or ſyluer they make them to be ſped and expedyed with floryns karolus at the pryce aforeſayde / and of leſſe ſome in valued pattars.</p>
                  <p>ALſo that none of what eſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycion he be of to preſume fromhenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to receyue or gyue: nor alſo to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (to whome ſo euer it be) pens enualued leſſer than pryce / nor at more pryce than this preſent ordynaunce bereth / nor alſo the pens declared for byllyon at any ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner pryce / by way of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mutacyon nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe in to the handes of chaungers as it is ſayd. On payne of forfeyture of the ſayd pens and of .l. karolus of golde for the fyrſte tyme. For the ſeconde tyme the ſayd pence and .C. karolus. And for the thyrde of .ii. C. karolus and other pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie arbytrary as aboueſayde.</p>
                  <p>WE alſo defende that none of what eſtate he be of to tranſporte or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to be tranſported or borne out of
<pb n="xl" facs="tcp:18518:45"/>
any of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees and ſygnoury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es any lyghte penyes of golde molten or vnmolten or any maſſes of golde or of byllyon. On payne of forfeyture of the ſayde penyes &amp; maſſes and of .ii. C. dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ryalles of golde for euery marke of golde / and of .C. ryalles of golde for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry marke of ſyluer for euery tyme / and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that ſo dothe.</p>
                  <p>WE defende alſo to al our receyuers our demaynes of our aydes / rentꝭ and other goodꝭ. To the mayſters of our chambres ol treaſoury / to the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſourers of our warres and our other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycers of receptes / herein compryſed our offycers of comptable Iuſtyce / that they do not receyue / gyue nor alowe gold nor ſyluer from one to another / for any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner cauſe at hyer pryce than we haue ordeyned. On payne of forfeytyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of a. M. karolus of golde / and loſſe of theyr offyces without euer to recouer them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18518:46"/>aNd for the more ſurete of the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of this preſent ordynaunce / we haue ordeyned (that all our offycers i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the townes &amp; other places of our countrees in theſe partyes) at the day that the ſame is proclaymed. Alſo the men of lawe of the ſayde townes and other places / to be preſent at the ſayde proclamacyon. And that the ſayde men of lawe make ſolem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pite othe vpon the crucyfyxe in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the ſayde pryncypall offycers of the ſayde places / inuyolately to obſerue the ſayde ordynaunce. And that all the bourgmayſters / mayres / ſhyryffꝭ / of our townes / vyllages / bourghes / and other lordſhyppes at the day of the renewyng of the lawes of the ſame beſyde the othes that they are wont to make by reaſon of theyr rowme to ſwere ſolempnely to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſayde ordynaunce of moneyes or that that we or our ſucceſſours at the ſayde tyme ſhall publyſſhe. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they and euery of them to theyr power to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyte and behaue themſelf at the Indy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyon / condampnacion / punyſſhement
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:18518:46"/>
and correccyon of the tranſgreſſours of the ſayde ordynaunce / and to the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the penalties and amendes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ordeyned after the tenour of the ſame. On payne yf they fayle to be at the ſaid proclamacyon (yf they be in place where it ſhal be) &amp; to make othe to the <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſeruyng of the ſame / as ſoon as they be in theyr of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce echone of a.L. karolus of golde of theyr propre goodes. And on payne that our ſayd offycers: and the ſayd ſheryffes and men of law be neclygent to procede to the indycature &amp; correccyon of the ſayd tranſgreſſours after that the faulte com to theyr knowlege of pryuacion of theyr offyces without euer to recouer them. And moreouer of .vi.L. karolus of gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for amendes eche of them of theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre goodes without delay or grace.</p>
                  <p>ALſo for our offycers of receyte &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce of audytours of our countrees and lordſhyppes / we ordeyne that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in .xv. dayes after the proclamacyon of the ſayde ordynaunce at the fertheſt they
<pb facs="tcp:18518:47"/>
make ſolempne othe for kepynge of the ſame in the handes of our audytours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom they are bounde to accompte. And yf they be ferre of / they may make the ſayde othe in the handes of the chyef Iuſtyce of acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes. And the ſayd othes made the clerkes of the courtes of Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce therof ſhall make a regyſtre.</p>
                  <p>WE ordeyne alſo that all oure offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers echone in the lymytes of theyr Iuryſdyccion / and the generalles of our moneyes and euery of them in all our countrees &amp; lordſhyhppes to enquere dylygently of the feate and doyng of our ſubgectes / and other reſydent and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng in our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees: &amp; yf they kepe the ſayd ordynaunce or not. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may the more eaſely com to the knowle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of the ſame: we haue gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon / power / auctoryte / &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; ſpecyally by theſe <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes ſyngulerly to our ſayd offycers to enquere / &amp; examyn by othe &amp; fayth al them whom they wyl yf they knowe any that hathe offended
<pb n="xlii" facs="tcp:18518:47"/>
(in theyr iuryſdyccyons) agaynſt this or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynaunce. And we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde all them that ben inquyred to tell the trouth / On payne of an .L. karolus of golde eche of them / or of other arbytrary payn. Ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge our offycers eche one in his Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyccyon to procede agaynſt the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders in the penalties ordeyned. And that the generalles of the moneyes reporte vnto vs of the offences that they fynde / or to our moſte dere and ryght welbeloued ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter the quene: or to our ſayd chyef &amp; men of our pryue counceyll &amp; of our fynaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to pouruey therin as it behoueth.</p>
                  <p>ANd that the ſayd penalties aboue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared be dyſtrybuted / the thyrde par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to our profyte / one thyrde parte to the accuſer / and the other thyrde to the profy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the offycer that dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly executeth the ſayd penaltie. And the ſaid penalties we wyll &amp; ordeyne to be executed precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely any oppoſycyon or appellacyon ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or to be made notwithſtanding. And yf any of the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>greſſours appele or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:18518:48"/>
fro execucyon of the ſayd penalties we ordeyne to the chyef preſedent &amp; men of our pryue and bye counceyll / &amp; to our chaunceller &amp; men of our ſayd counceyll in brabant / and to all offycers and men of lawe of the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree / and other in knowlege therof eche in theyr degre that they agre not to the ſayd appeales letters of releyf no: other prouyſyon conteynyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge clauſes of inhybycyon.</p>
                  <p>ANd for bycauſe that none ſhall prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ygnourau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in our ſayd ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and edyct / we wyll that it be proclay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med in all our townes and other places of our ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree of Brabant / where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as proclamacyons are vſed to be made the .xv. day of the next moneth of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre. And from that tyme forewarde eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry .vi. monethes withoute interrupcyon tyll by vs be otherwyſe ordeyned. And that the copyes in good legyble lettres be faſtened to the gates and other places of the ſayd townes &amp; churches of the ſayde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trees. ¶And alſo that the copyes of
<pb n="xliii" facs="tcp:18518:48"/>
the Inſtruccyons gyuen by the general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to the exchaunges of the ſayde coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lykewyſe tacked about the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce where as they abyde. Our ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce made in the yere .M. v. L. and .xx. to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the feates of money: wherof is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken afore with the ſurplus / in all poyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and artycles / the whiche by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent acte is not expreſſely derogate in the hole. And we gyue you in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ryght expreſſely ordeyne and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myt by theſe preſentes that our ſayd preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in all poyntes and artycles ye cauſe to publyſſhe the ſayde .xv. daye of Nouembre next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge in all the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of youre Iuryſdyccyons / where as proclamacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ben vſed to be done. And the foreſayd ordynaunce of the yere .M.v.L. &amp; .xx. in all poyntꝭ and artycles to the whiche by theſe is not expreſſely dero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gate as is aforeſayd ye preſerue / kepe / &amp; obſerue / and cauſe to be preſerued / kepe / &amp; obſerued in the maner called inuiolably And for the ſame procede &amp; cauſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede agaynſt the tranſgreſſoures of the
<pb facs="tcp:18518:49"/>
ſayde ordynaunces by execucyon of the penalties therin appoſed really in dede without delay / ſymulacyon / or forberyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge any oppoſycyon / or appellacyon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de or to be made notwithſtgndynge.</p>
                  <p>This for to do / and that theron depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth / we gyue you and your ſubſtytutes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted full power / auctoryte / and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpecyall. And by theſe ſame we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde expreſſely all our Iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / offycers and ſubgectes that ſeeth this and to euery of them in theyr degre / and as to hym apperteyneth in this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge / ye obey and intende dylygentlye / for it is our pleaſure.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>¶Gyuen in our towne of Bruxelles vnder our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre ſeale hereto put in placarde: <date>the .vii. day of the moneth of octobre. The yere of our Lorde .M. v. L. xxxi.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <signed>Thus ſubſcrybed. By the Emperoure in his counceyll. And ſygned of the ſecretarye Dublioul.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <argument>
               <pb n="xliiii" facs="tcp:18518:49"/>
               <p>¶Semblable ordynaunces by his mageſte haue ben expedyed and proclaymed in Flaundres / in Artoys / in Haynaw / in Luxembourg / in Namur / in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande / zellande / Fryſe / Vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rrecht / in Oueryſſell / and other countrees in theſe partyes.</p>
            </argument>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprynted by me Robert wyer, dwellynge at the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of ſaynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ngelyſt / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaynt Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyns paryſſhe in the byſſhop of Norwytche rentes beſyde cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge Croſſe. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:50"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ERT WYER</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18518:50"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
